Finding Aid for Benjamin Sawtell Hanchett papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Benjamin Sawtell Hanchett Papers 1858 and 1888-1958 1888-1931
Hanchett, Benjamin Sawtell, 1868-1933.
851397 Aa 2
Correspondence relating to politics and his activities as regent of the University of Michigan; also material concerning the depression and impact of the New Deal on agriculture in Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came to the library from Jacob Shoemaker and John Huizenga (donor no. 4032 ) in 1963.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Benjamin Sawtell Hanchett was a Grand Rapids, Michigan, farmer, businessman, and regent of University of Michigan, 1911-1929. Hanchett was born in Grand Rapids, October 1, 1868. After completing his education in the public schools of that city he began working for the Street Railway company of Grand Rapids as an office boy. He remained with the company, later know n as the Grand Rapids Traction Company, his entire career, rising to the office of president and general manager. In 1900-1901 he built the Grand Rapids, Holland and Lake Michigan Railway which was the first interurban railroad in western Michigan and served as president of the company for a time. Hanchett served three successive terms as mayor of the village of East Grand Rapids.
Hanchett was appointed t the University of Michigan Board of Regents in April 1911 to complete the term of Loyal E. Knappen of Grand Rapids who had resigned. He was elected in his own right in1912 and served until resigning in 1929.
Correspondence relating to politics and his activities as regent of the University of Michigan; also material concerning the depression and impact of the New Deal on agriculture in Michigan.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan.; Depressions--1929--Michigan.; Farmers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); New Deal, 1933-1939--Michigan.; Railroads--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; United States--Politics and government--1901-1953.; University of Michigan. President.; Grand Rapids Railway Company.
Contributors:
Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933.; Green, Fred Warren, 1872-1936.; Groesbeck, Alexander J., 1873-1953.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923.; Mapes, Carl Edgar, 1874-1939.; New, Harry S. (Harry Stewart), 1858-1937.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860; Townsend, Charles Elroy, 1856-1924.; Tuttle, Arthur J., 1868-1944.; Warner, Frederick Maltby, 1865-1923.; Weeks, John W.; Hays, Will H.$$g(Will Harrison), 1879-1954.; Smith, Alfred Emanuel, 1873-1944.
Genre Terms:
genre
- Correspondence
  - 1888-1922, 41 folders (Box 1)
  - 1923-1931 and undated, 30 folders (Box 2)
  - Family correspondence, 1858 and 1935-1958, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Other Materials
  - Young Men's Christian Association (Box 2)
  - Grand Rapids Country Club (Box 2)
  - Market Administration, National Recovery Administration, etc. (Box 2)
  - War Food Administration, Commodity Price Corporation (Box 2)
  - Code Authority, Wheat Flour Milling Industry (Box 2)
  - Indentures, and miscellaneous legal and financial materials, 13 folders (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
  - Printed miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Jenison family miscellanea (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea (largely University of Michigan related (Box 3)
  - Photographs (mainly unidentified) (Box 3)
  - Letterbooks containing copies of letters to employees (of Grand Rapids Railway Co.), other business communications, etc., 1892-1895, 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Letterbook containing copies of letters (mainly non-business), 1893-1897 (Box 3)
Selective Index to Correspondence
Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933.
Letter, Nov. 3, 1924, from Hanchett to Coolidge concerning Marion L. Burton; also letter of James B. Reynolds concerning Coolidge, Jan. 23, 1920
Green, Fred Warren, 1872-1936.
Letter from Howard C. Lawrence concerning the nomination of Green for Michigan governor, July 6, 1928.
Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923.
Letters to Florence and Warren G. Harding, June 23, Nov. 4, 1920, Aug. 2, 1923.
Also letters about Harding: Lewis C. Laylin letter, Feb. 25, 1920, George B. Christian letters, Nov. 4, 1920, Nov. 11, 1921, April 9, Apr. 25 and Aug. 2, 1923; Will H. Hays letter, July 10, 1920; John W. Weeks letter, June 23, 1920
Hays, Will H. (Will Harrison), 1879-1954.
Letter from Hays re Warren G. Harding, July 10, 1920
Mapes, Carl Edgar, 1874-1939.
May 12, May 19,1925.
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.
Aug. 20, 1918
July 11, 1919
Jan. 6, Feb. 20, Aug. 17, Dec. 25, 1920
Nov. 19, Nov. 21, 1923
Dec. 30, 1924
Feb. 25, Feb. 26, Mar. 2, Mar. 7, Mar. 21, Oct. 19, Nov. 3, 1925
Oct. 2, 1926
Dec. 20, Dec. 27, 1928
Aug. 22, 1929
Smith, Alfred Emanuel, 1873-1944.
Nov. 6, 1925
Townsend, Charles Elroy, 1856-1924.
Feb. 1, Oct. 27, 1921
Jan. 9, Jan. 16, Jan 20, June 3, June 24, June 28, June 30, Oct. 18, Dec. 25, 1922
May 12, May 19, 1925
University of Michigan. President.
Letter from Edward C. Lawrence re the office of president, Feb. 25, 1925
Warner, Fred Maltby, 1865-1923.
July 10, 1920
Weeks, John W.
Letter re Warren G. Harding, June 23, 1920